hello and welcome this is active
inference guest stream number
86.1 biological neurons compete with
deep reinforcement learning in Sample
efficiency in a simulated game world
with Faro Habib and mo kaj NAD and thank
you both for joining really looking
forward to the presentation and take it
from here thank you very much yeah
thanks Danielle um I guess I'll just uh
open up hello everyone thanks for
joining I hope this will be interesting
and fun for everyone uh so today uh we
are going to talk about uh a
collaboration between cortical Labs here
in Melbourne and mes
University uh we will mostly emphasize
on the details of the project as titled
biological neurons compete with deep
reinforcement learning in Sample
efficiency in a simulated game world but
before going into details of the
findings that we had in this study I'm
just going to uh talk briefly to uh our
setup our system of invitro neuronal
cultures that we are interacting with
and we are embedding them in simulated
game environments to be able to do all
these cool tests and uh well which has
led us to these
findings so to start with um
I'm going to just tell you what were our
motivations in cortical labs and what
led us to where we are here today uh
without getting too philosophical though
uh we can say that we as humans need
they
froze I'll just wait
their own uh shortfalls if you would say
for
example yeah
oh yeah sure okay
so uh reshare so it's stopped
sharing oh no no that's okay um so stop
share yeah uh
so yeah without getting too
philosophical here uh we can say that us
as humans we need intelligence in some
form to be able to disal me meaning from
the phenomena around us but to be able
to make more Intelligent Decisions by
Computing more data faster and with
better outcomes has actually become one
of the major goals and the holy grounds
of machine learning and AI in the past
decades uh now in search for different
ways of uh intelligent Computing uh one
way for us to C categorize all of our
recent efforts could be to talk about
these categories like machine learning
and AI Quantum Computing or neuromorphic
chips obviously there are other ways of
looking at these and uh other tools that
we've developed uh and they are all the
right tools for the right purposes but
uh they could all also have their own
pros and cons and what motivated us for
to look for new alternative ways of
computing was that for example in
machine learning and AI we are facing
challenges such such as their high
computational power uh high power use
their uh catastrophic forgetfulness or
the fact that they require very large
samples and very long training times and
they are also uh very susceptible to
errors or if you're talking about comput
Quantum Computing uh again we have
extremely high power usage uh these are
very isolated from the external world
and uh very prone to errors and they are
not very adaptable uh and also if you're
looking at the neuromorphic Computing uh
and the whole You Know Field around it
there's also uh limited error correction
capabilities uh variability between
circuits and also they still require
some sort of programming to some
capacity to be able to do what we are
designing them to
do so basically in search for this
alternative intelligent Computing
system uh that could actually solve some
of these challenges that we have in
these other categories we thought that
why not use the brain and the brain
cells themselves which are the most
advanced intelligent uh systems that we
know of and uh there's actually no need
to prove that these brain cells are
capable of doing very high order of
computation uh so I'm not going to go
into tooo many details of our setup
because I think many of you might have
heard or read about it but just to recap
firstly what we do in cortical Labs uh
to basically design and develop our
system is that we use human ipsc cells
which are then differentiated to a
neuronal phenotype for the studies that
we're going to talk to you about today
we also had primary cortical neuronal
cell cultures from mice and all of these
cell cultures were then plated onto
Maxim one high density multi- electroid
Aras which basically enables us to
stimulate the neurons and also record
from them at the same time from the same
cultures and uh well we see that we saw
and we showed that these cultures could
actually survive for even more than six
months on these multi- elector arrays uh
with our new products new systems in
this brain we can go even Way Beyond six
months and keep them healthy keep them
alive keep them active which gives us
capability of studying them for longer
terms and for example here is just a
sample microscopy Imaging but you can
see the dense interconnected
population uh of uh these neurons that
have been cultured and are active on the
m
electrod so then we designed what we
called initially dish brain which is
this Clos Loop real time system to
interact with these neuronal cultures
and embed them in the environments of
the arcade game of pong which you can
see here on the right hand side uh this
is a famous arcade game you have one
padal and basically the paddle is
playing against the wall trying to hit
the ball
accurately uh and uh the first published
work that we uh explained the system and
we showed you know basically uh all our
findings of the system uh uh you I think
you've seen it and you've talked about
it before but but it um basically
explores the system in extensive detail
which I will not bore you with here with
all of those details but because it's
important to know what's this closed
loop system that we're dealing with I'm
just going to briefly talk to talk you
through how uh it works and how it's
designed basically on each culture which
is integrated onto a multi exor array we
first predefined separate regions one uh
sensory region on top and two model
regions on the bottom of this uh cartoon
image that you can see on the left hand
side and the right hand side first using
the sensory region we feed information
about this hypothetical balls X and Y
AIS location so imagine that game
environment you have the ball moving you
want to know where it is in that frame
so the x-axis location is actually
uh encoded by rate coding between 4 and
40 htz depending on how close the ball
is to the paddel on the x- axis and also
we use Place coding uh where uh where we
encode where the ball is on the y axis
by only simulating one of the eight
available sensory electrodes within the
sensory region and these eight
electrodes are actually evenly
distributed along the y axis so
whichever part or segment the ball falls
into that sensory electrode is
activated then we record from these two
again predefined motor regions and
compare their activities of the all the
channels in those regions which are some
of them are representative of the up
movement as you can see the arrows on
this uh figure and some of them are
responsible for downward movement of the
paddle uh and then obviously comparing
the activities of these two
uh sub regions we decide where the
culture is moving the paddle in what
direction and then we need to close the
loop by applying feedback to the same
sensory region as we defined again this
is another schematic maybe it to make
things a bit more clear uh but basically
to explain our feedback loop what
happens is that if the ball is missed by
the paddle random unpredictable signal
is applied for like 4 seconds at random
sites in the sensory region and then if
the ball is hit accurately a predictable
repeated stimulation for a shorter
amount of time is applied to all of the
sensory
electrodes so we then again uh record
from these cells on top of the silicone
chips both during the rest State
spontaneous activity for comparison
reasons and during their embodiment in
the gameplay environment and I'm just
going to briefly touch upon something
you might all have been thinking of now
that I have explained our feedback loop
here that um after designing the system
and finding actually evidence that this
particular type of feedback loop is
actually enabling the neurons to be
learning the game or to be performing
the game better as uh we go on in time
uh you could think of this clearly as
some evidence supporting um free energy
pre
that we've been talking about for a long
time now uh the fact that uh these
neurons don't like surprised don't like
the unpredictable sensory feedback that
they receive when they miss the ball is
what seems to be driving them towards
playing the game better and towards
performing better in the game so this
was really cool evidence that we found
that could be actually explained by fvp
as we all know about uh we could
definitely talk more in detail about
this but uh I'm just going to uh just
going to go to our basically most newest
findings this is again a quick uh
illustration of the actual gameplay
environment on one of our meas this is
obviously the simulated environment you
can see the game play uh in the corner
top rights and how the all the channels
that we have on the
mea have these activities that we
recording from and then we are comparing
the two sides of the motor region to
actually decide uh what the culture is
doing in this gameplay
environment uh yeah and then we
evaluated their performance and whether
these are learning using several metrics
this is a very very short summary uh of
how the my cells and human cell cultures
which we call MCC and HCC compared to
our media only controls to our in
silicone models and to our neurons at
rest and they all show that they perform
much better with more significant
improvements in several metrics
including their average rally lengths
the percentage of Aces or Ace here is
actually a bad thing so Ace means a ball
is missed after the initial serve so the
lower the number of Aces gets the better
they're performing and also they showed
a significant Improvement in the
percentage of long rallies which we
defined as rallies that have more than
three accurate
hits again we've got uh you know much
more nuanced you know results and
details that we have figured out from
these systems but here you can see the
comparison between the first five
minutes in green and the second 15
minutes of each gameplay session in
Orange and you can see that's basically
the only significant Improvement
occurred in our human and mice cortical
cells uh now in our obviously never
ending search for the underlying
mechanisms that could drive this
Behavior Uh in one of our more recent
projects uh we first wanted to compare
the gameplay and rest sessions in terms
of their connectivity so the
connectivity between the different
channels that we are recording from and
how actually these connectivities are
changing over time and whether the
evolution in these connectivities can
capture uh parts of this learning or
this basically the plasticity we assume
that is happening uh during game play
and mo is going to take on from here
talk about all fundings from this
functional connectivity study and then
we're going to spend most of the time on
the comparison with the reinforcement
learning methods that we did in terms of
their sample
efficiency okay great
um hi everyone again uh now to do uh
this task that F mentioned uh first we
the challenge was that for U every
recording and for each Channel we have a
very very large time series of spiking
activity so to make these sparse U
sparing patterns more interactable and
easier to work with um first we decide
to we decided to use a dimensional the
reduction algorithm to bring each
channel Time series uh to a lower
dimensional space we used and compared
uh different um algorithms including
tisne and ISO map that you see here and
as we can observe interestingly uh even
in in a very low dimensional space such
as uh a 2d space
here um
the the first and second half of the uh
of each recordings were easily
distinguished during game play but uh
not uh clearly in the
rest these figures are for uh sample
cultures and the two colors represent um
all the channels in each half of the
recording so we were motivated to
continue this study in in this lower
Dimension uh dimension for higher
interpretability and lower computational
power
use but then also having
1,24 uh rep recorded channels still
meant High computational complexity in
our problem so we have this hypothesis
that most probably a lot of these
channels are highly correlated and uh we
might be facing redundancy of
information when looking at all the
availab channels in the
recording so for that reason we designed
this pipeline uh to eventually study the
functional connectivity of channels and
um compare between gameplay and
rest very briefly we first use uh tne
algorithm to map all channels according
to the lower Dimensions which is
selected to be Tre
here uh then to select a uh smaller set
of channels uh which are good
Representatives among all the recordings
we stacked up the low dimensional
representations of U all game play
sessions and using a Tucker
decomposition uh followed by a
kid um clustering algorithm we chose the
centroid of the channel uh clusters in
this low dimensional space as uh the
mutual representative channels
we tried different uh numbers of
clusters and got the best results uh by
choosing 30 clusters and higher numbers
of clusters show no significant
Improvement uh in the
results uh finally we built the uh
functional connectivity networks uh
using these 30 channels as notes and the
pearon correlation of their spiking
activities as the weight of the um ages
between each pair of
channels but we were also interested in
track tracking the connectivity Dynamics
and changes in time as learning occurred
in the
culture so what we looked at here was
the changes in uh correlation between
purs of notes from the first two minutes
to the last two minutes of the
recordings uh
[Music]
and what we see here um on on on the
left um and right are uh the average
networks from all of our recordings
which is around 300 Gameplay sessions
and about 150 res
sessions first of all uh
the extracted representative channels
which come from the sensor regions are
um in uh green circles and the ones from
motor regions are are in blue squares
now the color of the edges indicates an
increasing or decreasing correlation
between nodes in red and black
respectively and the ede thicknesses are
related to to the magnitude of these
differences simply by uh visualizing the
data uh uh we saw significant
differences between rest and gam playay
where we observe uh many more positive
edges or increase in correlation between
channels um and finally to give you some
more statistics of what we found um
happens as the network of channels
evolves in
time um here we can see the same five
measures of network Dynamics um compared
between the first and last two minutes
um in in pink uh and green and also game
play on top um versus uh rest rest
station yeah the game plays are in pink
and and the rest are in uh uh
green first uh we have the average
weight of the functional connectivity
networks uh which shows a significant
increase during game play but not at
rest next the modularity index uh that
decreases significantly but only at game
playay uh that basically means that the
different clusters or modules uh of the
network become more interconnected
during the game play as time goes
on the clustering coefficient also shows
a significant increase only in game
playay meaning that uh the neighbors of
a given node
uh become have become more strongly
connected between
themselves and finally um characteristic
path lens or the average shortest path
between any pair of nodes in the network
decreases significantly after 18 minutes
or game play
recording now that we have found even
more evidence of the Dynamics of these
networks which could potentially give
rise to emergent learning that is
observed in their
behavior in the in another study and
next study we were also interested to do
a direct comparison between uh the Deep
reinforcement learning algorithms and
our noral cultures in the same g game
environment of P but clearly um only
during the game
play we all know that uh RL algorithms
that use deep neural networks uh in
their structured have been developed to
beat human experts in various games such
as Atari games and have proven to be
very strong players of these games given
uh they have enough training but these
algorithms uh suffer from different
issues uh such as modeling the reward um
structure sample inefficiency
reproducibility as well as requiring
high levels of uh computing power and
these issues um suggest that deep RL
algor GMS might actually differ
fundamentally from Human learning
mechanisms and not be efficient to be a
plausible model for human learning
that's why we were motivated and
interested to do this research and
comparison um in our work we used three
deep RL algorithms
dqn um a2c and po which are established
to have good performance in Atari games
and our robust Tools in re enforcement
tasks particularly in games where the
input is an
image but apart from uh the traditional
gray scale image input of the game
environment we also take a step further
aiming to account for potential
adversaries resulting from The increased
dimensionality of the image input to the
de parl algorithms or so-called Cur of
dimensionality in U machine learning
terminology
we designed two additional types of
input
information first paddle and ball
position design where we obtain a four
dimensional uh Vector encoding the X and
Y coordinates of the ball and also the Y
coordinates of the paddles top and
bottom and also the ball position design
where uh we divide the uh y AIS of the
gam playay environment to eight equal
statments each mimicking one of the
sensory electrodes in the biological
cultures that place code the information
about the ball's y
AIS uh then the ball's uh xais position
is used as the second element of uh this
input Vector uh similar to the rate
coded component of the stimulation
applied to the B ological
cultures uh that we had uh this design
is the most uh similar one to the
cultures with the lowest dimension of
the input
vectors
um also we found that using the same
number of training game episodes for uh
biological neural networks and deep
reinforcement learning algorithms in the
image input design
the average rale lens is highest for the
human and mice cell cultures uh here in
uh orange and blue uh while uh they also
achieve the lowest percentage of
Aces uh and highest percentage of long
rallies may I just add here that uh
maybe it's if it's not been clear uh we
are training all of these for the same
number of episodes that the biological
neuronal networks had to be trained on
which was on average 70 game episodes in
20 minutes so just to make things as
Fair as possible we train these RL
algorithms also only for 70 episodes and
that's why we're talking about sample
efficiency here because we're going to
show you and we know that training them
for uh
very longer time would result different
obviously performances in these deire
algorithms yeah thank
thank then comparing the uh first five
minutes to the last 15 minutes of the
game um here in the third row um in
green and orange we see that only the
biological cultures show significant
Improvement in these
metrics next we repeated all the
analysis for the paddle and bulb
position input design which revealed the
fact uh that or algorithms performances
were not suffering uh from the Cur of
dimensionality and all the previous
conclusions still
hold and finally very similar
comparisons were observed when using the
last input design which was the most
similar to the biological cultures uh
input information structure once again
uh the RL algorithms are outperformed or
rarely match the biological cultures
performance at their
best and lastly we directly compareed
the relative Improvement in the average
lens of different groups over time um
and these plots show that
um in all the Tre designs um human cell
cultures uh show the highest Improvement
uh usually followed by the mousee C
cultures
we also compared the relative
Improvement in the average uh it counts
or average rallies between the first 5
minutes and the last 15 minutes for all
the sessions as well as the postto test
in each separate group for different
batch sizes and different
hyperparameters as we can see in the
first two rows and additionally as BR
mentioned we'll look at the mean total
reward of the RL algorithms with only
the image input design using the same um
hyper
parameters uh for an extended training
period of uh
11,000 uh game episodes in the last uh
and or third row here and it showed um
improved performance across an um
Extended number of training episodes
this is well as it anticipated 70 game
episodes or 20 minutes of
recording uh which is the same number
used to train the biological cultures
but not sufficient for um any of the
algorithms so we could eventually
conclude that the RL algorithms uh
showed the lowest sample efficiency
having the lowest improvements in
learning given the same number of
training episodes provided for all the
groups and this was even the despite the
fact uh that these methods receive a
higher information density compared to
cultures finally we also explored a
biologically inspired algorithm
implementing an active inference agent
that uses counterfactual
learning um improved learning rates
observed in this biologically inspired
learning protocol supports the potential
of active inference agents to provide
valuable insights into optimized
learning
strategies
so um and and they can enhance our
understanding of these
Dynamics however these active inference
algorithms are um still highly dependent
on on the chosen hyper parameters and um
require relatively higher power
consumption compared to biological
systems however these results highlight
the value of uh further exploring
biologically inspired systems of
learning and support the notion that uh
synthetic biological intelligence
systems may offer a useful Pathway to do
this um in in the
future so yeah I think I stop here and
uh let us thank all of our internal and
external uh
collaborators both in Monash University
and cortical labs and and in um other
institutes thank
you yeah can
C thank you
awesome okay many places to jump in well
thank you for sharing the results maybe
just while we're on this
slide uh with the active inference
H how was this agent constructed and and
how or was it the case that the neurons
consider
counterfactuals or how how did the
counterfactual come into
play want
to uh so here maybe this is actually a
bit bad uh naming with you so C here is
actually our contrafactual learning
agent and the number you can see in
front of it is its uh horizon horizon
horizon uh which is one of the
parameters we've adjusted then uh for
our uh search space uh we have tried to
mimic as much as we could um I should
mention also here that ashin ashin Paul
was uh the person who has helped us with
this analysis worth mentioning again so
for the search space we try to mimic
what we have in the biological cultures
so so the x axis which location of the
ball which we encode using the frequency
values between four and 40 Hertz in our
dish
brain uh we're mapped into basically a
space of 37 that would be 37 different
values along x-axis and our y- axis
eight different uh values which could be
uh given as
inputs uh so this would be our uh search
space or
environment uh and uh yeah so the we
explore different values of the hor
memory Horizon we could obviously go
even further but we were trying to find
a model that kind of matches the
biological cultures the best because as
as you all know uh we are thinking of
active inference as a plausible and
possible uh you know model of what is
actually happening in our brain uh so we
wanted to see if we can actually uh
reconstruct uh a model that is very
close to the performance of these
cultures so the Horizon memory of seven
uh basically having the seven frames
prior to the current step was what gave
us the closest
results yeah I think yeah uh just to add
I think a recent active inference scheme
is shown to be
mathematically equivalent to a part
particular class of neural networks
accompanied by some uh neurom
modulations of synaptic
plasticity and um it uses counterfactual
learning to accumulate a measure of risk
over time based on feedback from the
environment and a subsequent work that
validates this scheme experimentally
using invitro noral network has also
appeared recently in um Isam ra at Al
paper uh in 2022 yeah uh so yeah just to
I think more clearly answer your
question this was just a uh
contrafactual learning uh model on its
own it is not uh we are not using the
neurons or the input from neurons in the
model this is just a model Standalone
model on its own trying to mimic the
performance of the invitro
cultures cool like really interesting
how the same kind of functional play or
differing might arise from systems that
are explicitly comparing Alternatives
and systems that at
least are appearing to simulate
counterfactuals yet somehow the
instantaneous firing rate and the
response comes to act as if there is a
counterfactual in the sense that the
gradient is being compared and the
gradient is more often than not going in
the direction that
is leading to less surprising sensory
outcomes yeah exactly yeah okay I'll ask
a question from live chat um Jeff asks
is there a noise or density limit to The
Matrix culture
interconnect uh so by matrix culture I
am assuming they mean the multi- elector
array yeah that's very yeah uh so for
the results that we have uh talked about
today and most of our Publications up to
date we're using a Max one high density
multi and maybe we didn't State this
clearly we have 1,24 channels that we
are using for our design uh there are
thousands more channels but uh we are
only interacting with 1,24 of them so
maybe our limit we could say was 10,24
channels
but we are designing new systems now
that are actually less dense so we are
using a 64 channels in our
own chips designed at home at cortical
Labs uh this will yes uh limit Us in the
sense that we don't have as many
channels to be working with but also we
are hoping to be able to get more
interpretable uh results and uh let's
see interact more efficiently with the
cultures with the 64 8 by8
Matrix yeah oh noise yeah they also
asked about noise uh yes obviously uh we
are facing noise in any system any
experiment that we're doing we do have
the human IND IND noise we do have uh
noise when obviously recording from
these channels but we have have taken uh
as many measures as we could in order to
clean uh the recorded uh signals first
obviously we do filtering we do Spike
sorting uh we have tried to do template
matching with the waveforms with the
spike waveforms that we extract in order
to make sure we are not picking up any
false
positives uh and uh then after all these
steps done we are facing these rather
sparse spiking time series for each of
the recorded
channels cool um another question how
would you characterize why catastrophic
forgetting catastrophic forgetting
happens in RL and how do you feel that
active inference generative models Andor
the embodied dish brain averts that or
does it ever do forgetting or what kind
of forgetting and how how does the
Dynamics there differ from the reasons
why those phenomena happen in
RL yeah this this is a yeah this is a
great question um and one part of the uh
ongoing project that we are doing now um
regarding this question we are using
lifelong learning or continual learning
we are trying to teach the dish brain
and train the dish brain different tasks
multiple tasks instead of only one task
so far only Pawn game but we are
planning to train the system on
different
tasks and
see uh how they act um in different
consecutive tasks and without forgetting
the previous
Mones um we are still doing the
recordings we don't have the all the
results yet but yeah as as soon as we
got the recordings we can start the
analysis and see what happens Yeah so
basically yeah we don't have uh evidence
in our dish brain yet that catastrophic
forgetting is not happening that is on
our plan uh but uh just in terms of
comparison to RL like why catastrophic
forgetting happens in RL do you have any
insights on
that um
I'm not sure maybe um just one answer
that I can say now is that because most
of the orial algorithms use back
propagation in their
optimizations and maybe because of I'm
not sure but maybe because of the
gradient Vanishing and uh something like
that happens in their
training we can relate that that's the
the catastrophic forgeting to uh a and
because of the these these matters but
uh which is again exactly the point that
is in contrast with what's what we have
in an active inference model
and the generative models that we use
active inference but when we have the
multiple tasks in in our framework I
think we can answer this question much
better in in terms of what's happening
in biology and IND dish brain
yeah yeah just just to kind of highlight
that when there's a training loss
gradient in a neural network then
different tasks can have performances
that are at odds so even if you did
Epoch of training task a and task B you
might end up following the gradient for
task B so much that it deteriorates the
performance on on task a um so then the
active inference angle would be well if
you have a joint generative model and
you're going down down the free energy
gradient on the performance of both at
least you'd have the explicit Frontier
and you could explore like is there are
these gradients at odds like will there
be a trade-off with per tuning it one
way or the other um or is the
architecture such that it could
sustain the the the both functions at
once and then that would just be how the
generative model was parameterized it
wouldn't have invoked any kind of reward
model which especially as more and more
tasks into play becomes more and more
arbitrary to
specify exactly and the huge amount of
hyper parameters to be tuning which can
be again at OD with each other when
we're try training on more than one test
yeah cool so about like the sense in the
action
cells that is spatially fixed on the
chip so like how do those come to be
Associated is it just giving the sense
region what and what is given to the
action region such that it does
self-organize into that kind of
dynamic yeah so again the sensory and
regions or action regions that we have
were
predefined during design of dish brain
By Us by the founders of this Frame
mostly I would need to acknowledge here
again Han Andy and Brett uh but uh what
the challenge that we were facing
obviously is that we do not have any
ground truths or any uh map or layout
that the neurons give us to say okay yes
we are responsible of sensing we are
responsible of making an action
uh so because these are all the same
cell types so during the design of dish
brain what we did was we did experiment
trials and errors with different layouts
predefining different regions having uh
different roles and this is the design
we came to just because of the fact that
it showed better performance in the game
uh the sensory region is the region that
is receiving all the sensory input and
feed back and all of that there is no
input fed to the motor regions or the
action regions they are only being
recorded from and uh this is actually
what we are searching for to be able to
come closer to an answer of how these
are self-organizing themselves to be
acting the way they are acting one uh
way of looking at it was looking at the
functional connectivity networks which
we very briefly talk to uh to you about
here but in another project that is
ongoing here we've actually implemented
a
framework uh which uh which actually
showed us that looking at different game
episodes when the cultures are doing
well or bad in the game and
comparing uh an embedding or a lower
dimensional representation of all the
channels in these different uh episodes
showed us that during the better
episodes when the game performance is
High uh there is actually a nice uh
Association or correlation between the
activities of the sensory
region and then the motor regions which
are responsible for up movement and the
motor regions which are responsible for
down movement so they actually do make
these nicely uh separated clusters when
this does not happen during uh bad game
performance which was actually very nice
for us cuz um it showed us maybe these
pred definition of regions was towards
the right direction and more importantly
for our future designs we can actually
use this framework beforehand to see
what are the uh channels that are
clustering together self organizing to
be more Associated together more
correlated to then Define the uh
different rules roles for them we also
looked at uh the criticality metrics
actually in these cultures when they are
doing well in the game in terms of again
how maybe they are self-organizing
themselves uh in a specific matter that
helps them process information better
have higher storage capacity which is
all that criticality is actually showing
and in one of our recent uh studies
which is already published we did see
that during game play the whole
population is actually self-organizing
near a critical point and the sub
regions separately as well uh which is
actually a Hallmark of criticality being
uh scale free right so we did see this
scale free pattern in their activity as
well the motor region separately and the
sensory region separately both also
self-organized near
criticality which could be arising from
a nice balance between excitation and
inhibition but again there's lots to
explore and lots to look at
still wow very cool with the multi scale
criticality as those are the kinds of
like empirical patterns that in the
biological systems maximize the signal
intensity and and it's kind of first
principal statistical properties like it
wouldn't be using the dynamical system
to the full gain if it were falling far
on one side or
another and then to show that even
absent Gia and all these
other forcing or buffering elements that
that probably do play important roles in
the criticality being like maintained or
useful organism but then even stripping
out just the cells still has that
pattern just for what they expect and
prefer yeah exactly and we do hope in
our future iterations of the system by
the introduction of glal cells
asites we hope that this will actually
be again helping enforcing the how they
are self-organizing your criticality to
be performing the tasks to be processing
information however we want to phrase
that what kinds of like computational or
or system specific challenges do you
think this kind of system would be
useful for in like short and longer
terms but what what do you think and how
how does that work with plugging in and
co-evolving all of these like very
material details with the kinds of
settings that are
useful uh yeah so we do have this
uh here as a short list of what we are
thinking of as our short-term goals
long-term goals uh so as what we have uh
ongoing as ongoing
projects uh would be like what M
mentioned so we are as a first step
because if we are aiming to have these
computational units or biological
intelligent units we do want them to
show memory yeah to have the ability to
show this lifelong learning or continual
learning which we haven't uh ful shown
yet so that's one of our ongoing
projects to be able to uh train them in
different tasks U we are working on
different applications in drug Discovery
meaning that we can have invitro models
of different diseases such as epileptic
models for example and then uh testing
the drugs uh on our cultures to see not
only how the activity patterns are
changing uh but also even compar between
drugs and how effective each of them
are uh then um a recording capacity
actually uh with with these projects the
our previous recordings were just 20
minutes but now we can have recordings
up to in a month hours and hours and
yeah we have disability to record from
the cultures for I don't know up to 60
days oh way more than that which go up
to even 8 9 10 months and
ongoing uh but definitely it's going to
be new challenge because we have a huge
amount of data to analy but at least we
have a good source of recordings and
yeah yeah again in terms of challenges
yes the just analyzing the data the data
storage for our purposes is going to be
a challenge but it's really nice to keep
in mind that although it is a challenge
for us to maybe record have all of these
recordings and analyze them
computationally but these neurons these
cultures are still using very very tiny
amounts of power so the power
consumption by these computational units
if you want to call them is it still
very efficient which will hopefully in
the future enable us to potentially uh
use them as these Clos Loop uh
intelligence systems with these input
and output obviously uh design and I
think we we can go wild in our
imagination maybe someday they can even
replace silicone
chips interesting well
okay one question I guess to that is how
how do you think about the resourcing
and the
benchmarking like you could take take
the thermometer and give the temperature
reading that's kind of cool that it it
does have this fundamental physical
energy balance too so that's very
interesting but in terms of the
computation so here you explored some of
the
sample efficiency like how can these
different Computing substrates be
compared when it comes to like thinking
about speed but it doesn't have a clock
speed it's just unfolding or it doesn't
have a RAM memory or GPU measures for
parallelization so what what are like
promising or useful ways to understand
what these systems can
do yeah so uh one uh way that we are
exploring now again is that if uh we are
able to uh understand at least parts of
the mechanisms that that is driving this
learning that's happening or the
information processing that they are
doing one Avenue could be actually to
use those mechanisms Implement them in
uh what we know as machine learning or
AI methods and actually help to improve
those methods uh using these more
biologically inspired uh and more
intuitive mechanisms that we will be
hopefully
uncovering uh but in terms of just
comparing uh this was our first effort
comparison to RL in terms of sample
efficiency it was challenging to make
the comparison Fair we did have
suggestions we did have criticism in
terms
of as you saw it showed results that if
they are trained for longer durations of
times the AR methods obviously they can
even outperform our cultures at this
state but uh we all know that the PO
consumption now uh is like a huge issue
right even in these
llms new Hot Topic that everyone is
talking about uh if you just think about
how much power they
use uh I think just comparing in terms
of features like this their power
consumption that could give the
biological cultures a huge Edge uh and a
huge motivation for us to follow up on
you know on our designs and
just continue with what we're
doing uh do you have any ideas on how to
compare at this
stage uh honestly I think again the
continual learning the liftime learning
will be able to show us the actual
capabilities that that these biological
neuron networks can have uh the memory
if they show the memory that we expect
them to show uh could could be another
point of comparison between uh whatever
technology we have available now but
yeah lots to explore
still cool I guess to a different side
of it it says ethical considerations
like ongoing I mean even broadly what
does that look like or how does that
really come into play and get stewarded
in the
research uh
so uh when we started the research like
the start of all of that uh first of all
one of our challenge challenges was
always um just to put into wordss the
phenomena that we are seeing we are
observing that what is
happening uh because if you're using
terminologies like learning
cognition sentience and all of that this
uh could by itself be a huge area of
discussion and even dispute in some
cases uh but to start with our reason uh
to do this was that there is no
terminology like there is no set
language to talk about predefined
terminologies or language to talk about
these systems or these phenomena so we
decided to go with okay choose whatever
best describes them but then as we moved
on we realized that even the terminology
that we use could have uh could have
huge you know ethical controvers
controversies or cause uh people to
think about lots of ethical
considerations of are they sentient do
they feel and all of these so all of our
analysis that we're doing we are using
different metric different measures of
for example measures that have been
introduced to quantify Consciousness
like for example the PCI metric right uh
we can have all of these implemented for
our cultur which we are doing now and
then compare them against the findings
the state-of-the-art research that are
being done on Consciousness on cognitive
abil abilities and all of that and so
far to show that while these are capable
Computing units
they do not necessarily show or have the
features that would qualify them as uh
conscious features or units so these are
things some parts of the things that
we're doing we are trying to address to
move in parallel with all of our
computational studies in parallel do all
of
these uh basically analysis as well uh
to make sure that we are considerate
enough of a phenomena that we might not
be aware of it
happening underneath all of this but so
far uh we are happy to say that we have
published everything that we have found
we have been very open with uh our
findings and open to discussion open to
everyone's opinions about whether there
is an ethical angle that we have maybe
missed wow very interesting like how is
that Vector of different cognitive
performance on different tasks
associated with the
different measures of Consciousness and
are those like maybe some implicitly or
explicitly believe those are like the
same vector or that they're orthogonal
to each other and there's some other
kind of dimensionality where changing
the the cognitive capacity like on any
given t task ends up not or even
diminishing the performance in other
ways so it's like a whole portfolio of
evaluations because there's tasks but
then these are other measures and yet
it's like an opening up of these
measures into the empirical whereas even
before that it was from the qualitative
to the
formal but then all the equations on the
piece of paper don't get get to the
sensor reading so that will be quite an
exploration okay I'll just ask like one
or or any last questions um Jeff
writes have you compared results from
cultures from different brain structures
EG prefrontal cortex versus visual
cortex uh no that we haven't done all of
our research is based on these uh ipsc
cells which are differentiated into cour
IAL cells again in our future iterations
of the system we are introducing glal
cells Asos sites and all of that and we
are trying to also move to 3D organoid
uh intelligence systems or organoids but
uh we have not implemented or compared
between different brain structures
yet what what attributes or were there
any other things that correlated with
like the human the mouse difference I
mean do they are they different sized or
do they have different branching
characters uh
so they uh I'm not sure about the size
to be honest uh I would love to have one
of our biology team to be here to answer
that so I don't want to mislead anyone
but in terms of their characteristics uh
we did study them in terms of their
connectivity patterns like the study we
showed you about and the the Dynamics of
the
connectivity uh and we do see maybe we
could call it
slower plasticity mechanisms happening
at a slower rate which is what is uh we
saw in comparing mice and human cortical
cells which could explain parts of the
difference in the performance that we
saw but still we shouldn't forget that
even the mice cortical cells were
performing quite well uh in the context
of the task that we defined for
them wow very uh
interesting do you have any oh go ahead
they're quite
smart yeah even when alone it's like it
reminds me of kind of a lot of the
laboratory experiments in ant colonies
where even taking a nesme out of its
usual Collective Niche which is kind of
it's anous like other nestmate
interactions that's like other neural
connections um but with a more Dynamic
topology and then the GLE Niche is kind
of like the nest architecture and then
even stripping them of all of that and
the phermones and the tunnels and the
nest mates interacting and then it's
like still they could do the t-
maze um okay one one last question from
the live chat Jeff wrote could you see
scaling this from a 2D grid to 3D Matrix
emulating cortical columns and
interconnecting them yeah I think I
briefly mentioned that yeah but we are
actually doing it right now we are uh
working on organoids which is basically
the 3D structure that uh Jeff is talking
about uh one major challenge of organoid
the studies is always recording is yes
exactly how do you record from the cells
on the outer layer how do you make sure
the inner layer cells are still alive
and functioning and how do you
efficiently record from them without
causing any damage or major Interruption
to the activity of the organoid of of
the other layers but I think those are
challenges that everyone in this field
are trying to solve now are facing we
are also trying the same but we are
doing that we already have some
recordings of our organoids which are
comparing against our two is right now
uh no results to show unfortunately that
is very new but yes that is on our to-do
list cool do you have any last comments
or questions or like anything else you
want to
add no I think that was pretty much that
yeah I wanted to discuss and talked
about what could what could someone
who's learning and applying active
inference do in terms of their research
and learning to kind of dovetail with
these
[Music]
directions
um to model them more biologically
inspired yeah yeah know yeah so maybe if
if you would like to because of it's
still an open question for us to to
understand and realize the learning
mechanism Behind These biological
cultures and we need to find a way to
somehow model the
learning we were thinking about yeah
active inference for a long time as a
biologically inspired
algorithm but definitely uh there's a
long path
and uh lots of things that we can do
yeah and for someone who is interested
who's starting up I think although we
have done this comparison that we showed
you already but uh still we are looking
for uh proof or stronger evidence of
these for example biological cultures
actually following an active
inference kind of framework if you want
to say so it could be a very nice
starting point to actually model the
exact game environment that these
cultures these biological cultures seem
to be handling quite well in an active
fence uh and and later on very soon for
lifelong learning actually we we need a
mathematical analysis to model the
system yeah to start so to start with
with an environment or with a search
space exactly similar to what the
cultures are facing trying to build uh a
model upon that which matches the
activity of our neurons of the
biological cultures as we did but still
again starting from that point done they
will have a lot to explore we're happy
to uh discuss with anyone who's
interested to contact us via email in
calabs we have Discord Channel we have
all the means of communication that you
can think of so if they're interested to
you know get a sneak peek or have some
some sample data to work with definitely
happy to stay in touch with
them awesome thank you both so much it's
really fascinating so hope people
enjoyed it and learned it was great and
good luck thank you very much for
inviting us it great and pleasure yeah
thanks a lot for the invitation hope we
had some you know new stuff to show
people some good takeaways for the
audience thanks a lot thank you see you
bye see
bye
e for